Hello I'm professor Barba and I want
to introduce you to Jupyter. Jupyter is a
set of open source and free tools for
interactive computing, for thinking with
computing, and learning with computing.
Once you have installed Jupyter in your
machine, in your computer, and you have -- or
you have a cloud Jupyter service -- you
will see what is being shown in my
screen. This is the Jupyter dashboard, a
file explorer, in this case I have no
files, so I will create a new Jupyter,
Jupyter notebook. The notebook is the
basic format, document format of Jupyter.
I will click on the button that says new,
here on the top right, and I will have
perhaps some different options, you will
have some different options but there
are we will choose Python 3, and this
launches a new tab in my browser with an
empty Jupyter notebook. Here where it
says untitled I may choose to give it a
title, in this case say I want to call it
Jupyter demo, my first demo for you today.
Ok, that's my file name, and you see here
an inviting cell with nothing in it. The
cell is the chunk of content in a
notebook, and I can use different types
of content - it can be code, computer code
or text that can be formatted using
markdown. So let's choose markdown. Here I
have an option, a pulldown menu where I
can choose to change the cell into
markdown. Markdown is a way to format
text for a browser that has a few simple
marks to indicate for example a heading.
In this case I could use one hash to
indicate Jupyter demo as my title, I
could use two hashes to indicate the
heading that comes after that, say play
with strings,
that's our demo for today, and then
regular text has doesn't have any
markings, I could say
"it's fun" say, or maybe I want to use an
indication for italics, which is the
underdash, "really fun".
Okay, that is a little bit of text that I
have entered into a markdown cell, and to
obtain the formatted text I have to
Shift-Enter to execute that cell. And
immediately I get a new cell, that is by
default code. So let's write some code in
there. The first program that everybody
writes is print "hello world". in Python
the print function is simply print, we
use round brackets to mark what is going
to be the parameters that we give that
function. So the parameters in this case
is a single string "hello world". If I do
Shift-Enter, that executes the code cell,
and I get the output of Python's print
function which is in this case "hello
world". I could perhaps want to save this
string "hello world" into a variable. Let's
call it my_string. my_string equals - the
equal sign is the assignment operator in
Python - and I indicate a string with the
double quotes "hello world". And here I
have assigned a string to this variable.
So now I could, say up here print my_sting.
Notice that I have gone back up
to a cell, and I can re-execute that
cell and obtain its output.
The output is the same in this case. Let
me delete this cell to make more space. I
have my string and I want to
perhaps add an exclamation point. So in
Python I can add strings together,
concatenate is at the technical word, by
just using the plus sign. So let's
call that new-string equals my_string
plus quotes,to indicate string, and the
exclamation point and it's to enter, to
get a new piece of code in the same cell,
print new_string
and I Shift-Enter to execute and obtain
the result which is "Hello world" with now
an exclamation point. The next fun thing
that we can do with strings is to access
different characters in that string with
these square brackets. The square
brackets, with an index inside that marks
the position of that character. Python
uses indexing starting at 0, so the first
element of new_string would be
new_string square brackets 0. And if I
Shift-Enter to execute, I get the capital
letter "H" which is the first element of
"Hello world!". Similarly I could change
that to be 1 and I will get the second
element, that is the letter "E". And here's
a cool thing: you can use -1 to
indicate the last element of the string;
Shift-Enter that is the exclamation
point. So that's a very cool thing that
you can do with Python indexing into
strings. Another cool thing that you can
do is called slicing. Let me add here... so
here I have a empty cell. I'm gonna move
it up using that arrow in the top menu,
and I'm gonna change that cell into
markdown, to leave some notes to myself
for the future. And I'm gonna say here
that this is my -- I'm gonna use one
asterisk... two asterisks, to bold some text --
and I'm going to say: "Slicing strings" as
a little heading here. And instead of
using a single index now we're going to
use two indices. So how do we do slicing,
we use the name, name of the variable
nameOfstring -- let's call it that,
how about that,  equals... no so with the
square brackets, start colon end, that is
the syntax for a slice. But one thing to
notice here, is that the last or the end
index is not inclusive.
So these these are my notes to self for
the future, and I am going to use a slice
here. So what how could I get perhaps the
first word of "Hello world!" -- "hello". So "hello"
0 1 2 3 4 5 -- 5 would give me the first
letter , sorry -- the first word, "hello".
Maybe I want to get the last word.
new_string, that would be from 0, oh how about
so 6,  how about we find what the last
element is here. Oh we already know
how to do that it's -1. so what is
that -- "world". And this is just an
introduction to slicing and some cool
things that you can do with strings on
Jupyter. If you want to learn more about
playing with strings on Jupyter
notebooks we have a full lesson that is
called play with data in Jupyter, you can
find it on github, and it explains in
detail how to work with Jupyter, how
to open a new one, how to in this case
even launch the Jupyter application, how
to use different types of content in a
markdown cell, and then the different
operations that you can do with strings
right down here at the bottom. This is a
full lesson that you can read at your
own pace and follow along in your
Jupyter installation or in a cloud
Jupyter service. That's our first demo I
hope you'll be back for more.